So the concept of fundamentalist is essentially linked to
근본주의의 개념은 본질적으로
the concept of measurement in quantitmecs
양자역학에서 측정의 개념과 연결되어 있어
before point mechanics was developed
양자역학이 발전하기 이전에는
there it was generally a knowledge
과학자들 사이에 일반적으로 알려진 사실이 있었는데
by scientists that if you have a system that this
어떤 계가 있을 때
will the term in the state
그 계가 특정 상태에 있으면
and you perform a message on it you're gonna get
측정을 수행하면
a very well that i mean outcome i
아주 명확한 결과를 얻을 수 있다는 거야
want to mechanics that's no longer the case you can have
양자역학에서는 더 이상 그렇지 않아, 계가
a system that is in a perfectly well defined estate
완벽하게 잘 정의된 상태에 있을 수 있는데
and yet when you put from certain
그럼에도 불구하고 특정
measurements and it you can get run the outcomes
측정을 하면 무작위 결과가 나올 수 있어
so in order for me to illustrate that concept i be better i
그 개념을 잘 설명하기 위해서
need to bring the concept of super position
중첩의 개념을 가져와야 해
superposition is it's a concept that is not in here liquid
중첩은 여기에만 있는 개념이 아니야
is is is it's based on assistant displaying
여러 상태의 선형 결합이
several linear combination of states at
동시에 나타나는 것에 기반을 두고 있어
simultaneously and you can think of it
동시에 존재하는 거야, 그리고
as for example a radio wave carrying
예를 들면 여러 다른 주파수를 가진
many different frequencies there's nothing
라디오파처럼 생각할 수 있어, 거기엔
in human requirement about that
인간적인 제약이 없어
what gives the point on flavor to spread position is the fact
중첩에 양자적 특성을 부여하는 건 바로
of measuring the system
계를 측정한다는 사실이야
so i will instrument with an example
예시를 들어서 설명할게
imagine you have a system of faros
화살표들로 이루어진 계가 있다고 상상해봐
and you prepare the system
그 계를 준비해서
so that all the arrows are pointing left
모든 화살표가 왼쪽을 가리키게 해
and then you go and you
그러고 나서
as the existing the question are you up or down
위아래 중 어디를 가리키냐고 질문을 해
and us every apple so because the irish point in left can be
그러면 화살표가 왼쪽을 가리키기 때문에
express company described
표현하자면
as linux of the position between
위와 아래의 중첩으로
up and down you will get
설명할 수 있어서
out terms of our fifty percent up
결과의 50퍼센트는 위
and fifty percent when you ask the question are you open
50퍼센트는 아래가 나와, 위냐고 물어보면
you get that result from their system
그 계에서 그 결과를 얻게 돼
and then you can prepare with that at
그리고 나서 다른 상태로 준비할 수 있는데
a different state of the system where have
절반은 위를 가리키고
there also pointing up and have all their
절반은 아래를 가리키는 상태로
point in that and you asked the same question
같은 질문을 하면
and you get the same result
같은 결과가 나와
there are two very different systems
이 두 계는 아주 달라
and you have got this information
그런데 지금 이 정보를 얻었어
for for for a massive now
꽤 오랫동안
how can you determine what the difference is the
그럼 차이가 뭔지 어떻게 알 수 있을까
the citizens are very different
두 계는 아주 달라
because in the first case you have prepared the system in
첫 번째 경우에는 계를
a pure state many suck western you
순수한 상태로 준비했기 때문에
can ask to the system that will give you a deterministic
계에 결정론적인 답을 줄 수 있는
not run them out and that question is a you left all right
무작위가 아닌 질문을 할 수 있어, 그 질문은 왼쪽이냐 오른쪽이냐야
is going to tell you a hundred percent there left
100퍼센트 왼쪽이라고 알려줄 거야
in the second case there is no question you crash
두 번째 경우에는 물어볼 질문이 없어
you can ask them give you a hundred percent that then we
100퍼센트 결과를 줄 수 있는 질문이 없어, 왜냐하면
stick resolve because he's a mixture
혼합 상태이기 때문이야
so if you ask left for right
그러니까 왼쪽이냐 오른쪽이냐 물어보면
going to be around because half of them are up
무작위가 나올 거야, 절반은 위이고
of the down if you ask apple down
절반은 아래니까, 위아래를 물어봐도
same thing there's gonna is gonna be fifty percent
마찬가지야, 50퍼센트가 나올 거야
how did this this relate to one thing random
이게 무작위와 어떤 관련이 있냐면
so you can imagine that being
동전 던지기랑
similar to flip in a coin is going to be hassle tales
비슷하다고 생각할 수 있어, 앞면 뒷면이 나오니까
but is not like fifty nine coin a toll
하지만 동전 던지기랑 완전히 같지는 않아
because when you flee because
왜냐하면 동전을 던질 때
the only reason you don't know the result you're going to date
결과를 모르는 유일한 이유는
is because you don't know this
모르기 때문이야
energy with which a flip that calling the angle moment in
동전을 던진 에너지, 각도, 순간,
the ambient conditions in the room
주변 환경 조건
and so on for so if you knew all those
기타 등등을 몰라서야, 그래서 그런
variables you could predict castle tale there
변수들을 다 알면 앞면 뒷면을 예측할 수 있어
viables that are hidden today to the observer
관찰자에게 숨겨진 변수들이야
and for a lot of years scientists thought that there was
오랫동안 과학자들은 양자역학에도
similar variables in guantanamo extent will
비슷한 변수들이 있다고 생각했어
reveal themselves as as randomness
그게 무작위로 나타나는 거라고
and it wasn't until the
그건
seminar work off john bell in the sixties that actually
60년대 John Bell의 seminal한 연구가 나오기 전까지였어
it was demonstrated that that's not the case
실제로 그렇지 않다는 게 증명됐어
and now every physicist
지금은 모든 물리학자들이
acknowledges that there is no hearing
숨겨진 변수가 없다는 걸 인정해
but it will theory that is compatible with going to mechanics
양자역학과 양립할 수 있는 숨겨진 변수 이론은 없어
so it is really true that when you measure a system
그러니까 계를 측정할 때
a nature revealed from the
자연이 드러내는 건 진짜로
doesn't matter how long i think about that is i
아무리 생각해도 나는
will respond that amazing
그게 정말 놀랍다고 생각해